{"tossups": [{"question": "A Cheyenne scout killed this man\u2019s ally Looking Glass during a skirmish in the Bears Paw Mountains. This man succeeded his father, Tuekakas, and they shared the same Christian name. This man gave a speech in 1877 during his surrender to General Oliver Howard in which he declared, \u201cI am tired of fighting.\" Howard had followed this man\u2019s tribe for 1,100 miles as they attempted to retreat to Canada from Idaho. For ten points, name this 19th century chief of the Wallowa band of the Nez Perce.", "answer": "Chief <b><u>Joseph</u></b> the Younger (accept Young <b><u>Joseph</u></b>; or <b><u>Hin-mah-too-yah-lat-kekt</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The archer Tripurantaka and the dog-riding Bhairava are avatars of this deity, the patron of yoga, meditation, and the arts. The Ganges flows from the hair of this rider of the white bull, Nandi. The five mantras of this god reflect the sacredness of that number for this deity, whose sons by Parvati are Kartikeya and Ganesha. Brahma and Vishnu join this blue-throated god to make up the Trimurti. For ten points, name this Hindu destroyer-god who possesses a third eye.", "answer": "<b><u>Shiva</u></b> (or <b><u>Mahadeva</u></b>)", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {"question": "This conflict coincided with John Doukas\u2019s recapture of Rhodes, Smyrna, and Ephesus. Prior to this conflict, Peter the Hermit led pogroms against Jews in the Rhineland Massacres before rampaging through Hungary. This conflict first came about after Emperor Alexios I Komnenos called for western aid against the Seljuq Turks at the Council of Clermont. For ten points, name this Crusade called by Urban II which established the Kingdom of Jerusalem in the Holy Land.", "answer": "<b><u>First</u></b> Crusade (accept <b><u>Princes'</u></b> Crusade)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Gerald L. Geison [[GAY-sohn]] showed that this scientist had used deception when reporting his results. This scientist discovered that earthworms could bring diseases to the surface by studying animals dying in \"cursed fields.\" This scientist applied his findings from studying chicken cholera to create the first anthrax vaccine. This scientist dried out infected nerve tissue from rabbits to create the world's first rabies vaccine. For ten points, name this French biologist who names the process of heating milk to kill microorganisms.", "answer": "Louis <b><u>Pasteur</u></b>", "metadata": "Science - Biology"}, {"question": "A presidential candidate from this party continued a speech despite having a bullet lodged inside him after an assassination attempt by John Flammang Schrank. This party, later revived for reformer Robert La Follette\u2019s [[luh-FAH-lets]] 1924 presidential run, first formed after William Howard Taft beat an opponent at the RNC. This party\u2019s first candidate campaigned on Women\u2019s Suffrage and a continuation of his Square Deal program from the early 1900s. For ten points, name this party formed by Theodore Roosevelt to run in the Election of 1912.", "answer": "<b><u>Progressive</u></b> Party (accept <b><u>Bull Moose</u></b> Party)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In this musical, one of the title characters lends a copy of <em>Uncle Tom\u2019s Cabin</em> to a slave named Tuptim. Based on Margaret Landon's work of historical fiction, in this musical a widow and her son leave India for the promise of a job as a governess and a \u201cbrick house.\u201d In one song in this musical, Anna asks the grandson of Rama I, \u201cShall I Tell You What I Think of You?\u201d For ten points, in what Rodgers and Hammerstein work does Anna teach the wives and children of Mongkut, the ruler of Siam?", "answer": "<em>The</em> <em><b><u>King and I</u></b></em>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Misc Arts"}, {"question": "Philip II decreed that this substance was essential for Andean natives to consume but should not be used for religious purposes. This crop was targeted by an Andr\u00e9s Pastrana Arango initiative with Bill Clinton's support in which it was attacked via aerial fumigation. That initiative, Plan Colombia, also attempted to coerce farmers into not producing this raw material which was being processed into a drug by FARC. For ten points, name this plant, the source of a narcotic whose freebase form, \"crack,\" named an \"epidemic\" in the U.S. during the 1980s.", "answer": "<b><u>Coca</u></b> (accept <b><u>Cocaine</u></b>; accept <b><u>Coke</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "The Ute [[YOOT]] Pass is directly north of this mountain which inspired Katherine Lee Bates to write the lyrics to \u201cAmerica the Beautiful\u201d after a visit there. This mountain in the Front Range is the easternmost \"Fourteener,\" or mountain above fourteen thousand feet, in the U.S. The namesake of this mountain mapped the course of the Arkansas and Red Rivers during an 1806 expedition. The explorer Zebulon [[ZEB-yoo-lun]] names, for ten points, what \u201cpeak\u201d west of Colorado Springs?", "answer": "<b><u>Pike\u2019s</u></b> Peak", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "Until the formation of this government, Eugene Levin\u00e9 [[yoo-ZHEN leh-vee-NEH]] led a short-lived Soviet Republic in a southern state of this government's country. Polish Marxist Rosa Luxemburg co-led the Spartacus League against this government, leading to her execution by the Freikorps [[FRAI-kohr]]. Hyperinflation caused by this government occurred in part because of their need to pay reparations to the Allies, per the Treaty of Versailles. For ten points, name this German government which collapsed during the rise of Adolf Hitler.", "answer": "<b><u>Weimar</u></b> Republic (or <b><u>German Reich</u></b>; accept <b><u>Weimar</u></b> government; prompt on \u201cGermany\u201d or \"German Republic\")", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This politician responded abrasively to Jerry Falwell in response to his opposition regarding the appointment of Sandra Day O'Connor. In response to the Packard Commission, this man worked with William Flynt Nichols to create a bill that increased the power of the Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff. Despite being bolstered by Ronald Reagan's \"A Time for Choosing\" speech, this man was soundly defeated in the Election of 1964 by Lyndon B. Johnson. For ten points, name this Arizona politician, credited with laying the foundation for the Conservative Revolution.", "answer": "Barry <b><u>Goldwater</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "While leading military forces during this conflict, General Raoul Salan attempted a putsch staged from Corsica with support from Governor General Jacques Soustelle. The new Fifth Republic managed to negotiate the \u00c9vian Accords, ending this conflict and allowing France to retain the naval base at Mers El K\u00e9bir. The end of this war resulted in the mass emigration of <em>Pied-Noirs</em> [[PYAY-NWAHR]] to mainland France. For ten points, name this war between France and the National Liberation Front.", "answer": "<b><u>Algerian</u></b> War of Independence (or <b><u>Algerian Revolution; or War of [a]1</u></b> <b><u>November</u></b>; do not accept \"Algerian Civil War\")", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "The name of this movement may have been coined by critic Clarence Cook. This movement's founder was depicted in the painting <em>Kindred Spirits</em> by Asher Brown Durand. A visit to Northampton, Massachusetts inspired a work by one artist from this movement titled <em>The Oxbow</em>. This movement's founder drew from ancient Roman sculpture for paintings like <em>Destruction</em> in his <em>Course of Empire</em> series. For ten points, name this American art \"school\" founded by Thomas Cole and named for a body of water in eastern New York.", "answer": "<b><u>Hudson River</u></b> School", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "This man regarded Johnny Torrio as a mentor and William Hale Thompson as a business partner. A Baltimore hospital treated this man's neurosyphilis with one of the first-ever doses of penicillin. The Justice Department convicted this man for tax evasion, leading to his replacement as \"boss\" by Frank Nitti. Seven North Side Gang members died by this man's order in the 1929 Saint Valentine's Day Massacre. For ten points, name this Prohibition-era bootlegger and leader of the Chicago Outfit.", "answer": "Al <b><u>Capone</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "A novel by this author centers on the intersex Laurence and is titled <em>The</em> <em>Hermaphrodite</em>. This author published the Mother's Day Proclamation as an \"Appeal to womanhood\" following the Civil War. Inspired by a William Steffe song, this person wrote a work which features the chorus \"Glory! Glory! Hallelujah!\" which was written after hearing some soldiers sing \"John Brown's Body.\" For ten points, name this woman who married the founder of the Perkins School for the Blind and composed the \"Battle Hymn of the Republic.\"", "answer": "Julia Ward <b><u>Howe</u></b>", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Misc Literature"}, {}, {"question": "A woman who stalked this man, Princess Catherine Radziwill, wrote a pamphlet defending his character titled <em>The Resurrection of Peter</em>. This man, who orchestrated the Jameson Raid, led the defense of Kimberly during the Second Boer War. A <em>Punch Magazine</em> cartoon depicted this figure as a Colossus with his two feet on Cape Town and Cairo, referencing a railway he hoped to build. For ten points, name this founder of the De Beers Diamond Company who names a scholarship which gives students a full ride to the University of Oxford.", "answer": "Cecil John <b><u>Rhodes</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "In 1985, members of this religion carried out the Narita International Airport bombing. After the murder of his father, one leader of this religion began wearing swords representing temporal power and spiritual authority. Members of this religion assassinated Indira Gandhi in retribution for her strike on the Golden Temple in Amritsar, Punjab. Followers of this religion hold that their sacred text, the Adi Granth, is the final guru. For ten points, name this monotheistic Indian religion whose male followers wear turbans.", "answer": "<b><u>Sikh</u></b>ism", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {}, {"question": "After openly testifying about this military event, abolitionist Silas Soule was killed by a fellow militiaman for outing his commander to a Samuel Tappan-led Congressional tribunal. This event was perpetrated by the \u201cFighting Parson,'' John Chivington, and occurred after he ignored a white flag raised by Southern Cheyenne leader Black Kettle. For ten points, name this 1864 \u201cmassacre\u201d of Cheyenne and Arapaho women and children near a namesake Colorado tributary.", "answer": "<b><u>Sand Creek</u></b> Massacre (accept <b><u>Chivington</u></b> Massacre before mentioned; accept Battle of <b><u>Sand Creek</u></b>; prompt on answers indicating a massacre of Native Americans)  The Texas Mounted Rifles drew with Chivington\u2019s Union forces at the Battle of Glorieta Pass in what is now this U.S. state which entered the Union in 1912.  ANSWER: <b><u>New Mexico</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man's last finished novel features William Pitt Ferrars, whose sister is a companion to Adrian Neuchatel, titled <em>Endymion</em> [[en-DIM-ee-on]]. This man ordered Robert Napier to invade Ethiopia. This man also enacted the Public Health Act and introduced competitive exams for Civil Servants. Politically, this man traded power with William Gladstone. A favorite of Queen Victoria, for ten points, who was this Conservative politician, the only Jewish British prime minister?", "answer": "Benjamin <b><u>Disraeli</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "Common type of nonviolent protest against businesses involving refusal to purchase products utilized by that organization", "answer": "<b><u>Boycott</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "1875 act, supported by the earlier Page Act, meant to limit Asian workers supported by the Knights of Labor", "answer": "<b><u>Chinese Exclusion</u></b> Act", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Rival union led by Samuel Gompers", "answer": "<b><u>American Federation of Labor</u></b> (accept <b><u>AFL</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Man who succeeded Uriah Smith Stephens as leader of the organization", "answer": "Terence V. <b><u>Powderly</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Late 19th century depression that largely ended the importance of the organization", "answer": "<b><u>Panic of 1893</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Railroad tycoon opposed by the organization who attempted to corner the gold market with James Fisk", "answer": "Jay <b><u>Gould</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Woman who travelled the country giving her \"Dignity of Labor\" speech as an investigator for the Knights of Labor", "answer": "Leonora <b><u>Barry</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "1887 massacre of Black sugar cane workers in Louisiana sparked by a Knights of Labor strike", "answer": "<b><u>Thibodaux</u></b> [[TIB-ah-doe]] massacre", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Cathedral he had built commemorating the seizure of Kazan and whose architect he legendarily had blinded", "answer": "<b><u>Saint Basil</u></b>'s Cathedral (accept Cathedral of <b><u>Vasily the Blessed</u></b>; accept Cathedral of the <b><u>Intercession of the Most Holy Theotokos on the Moat</u></b>; accept <b><u>Pokrovsky</u> </b> Cathedral)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Architecture"}, {"question": "Secret police he created to serve as his bodyguards", "answer": "<b><u>Oprichnik</u></b>i (accept <b><u>Oprichnina</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Major city in which that secret police force committed a massacre in 1570", "answer": "<b><u>Novgorod</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Period started after the death of his son which ended with the rise of the Romanovs", "answer": "<b><u>Time of Troubles</u></b> (accept <b><u>Smuta</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Ineffectual son who succeeded him, the last Rurikid tsar", "answer": "<b><u>Fyodor</u></b> I Ivanovich (accept <b><u>Feodor</u></b> the Bellringer)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Former member of Ivan's personal guard who became the first non-Rurikid tsar of his country", "answer": "Boris Fyodorovich <b><u>Godunov</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Crimean Khan who was aided in burning Moscow by boyars who were terrified of Ivan's madness", "answer": "<b><u>Devlet I</u></b> Giray (accept <b><u>Giray</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "President elected in 2016 who has been criticized for his extremely harsh penalties against drug users", "answer": "Rodrigo <b><u>Duterte</u> </b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "Sea it shares with Vietnam and Indonesia that has been the site of territorial disputes with a country that claims everything within a \"nine-dash line\"", "answer": "<b><u>South China</u></b> Sea", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "Dictator who was forced to flee to Hawaii after being removed in a 1968 revolution", "answer": "Ferdinand <b><u>Marcos</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Politician who opposed that leader and whose assassination at Manilla International Airport led to massive protests", "answer": "<b><u>B</u></b>enigno <b><u>Aquino Jr</u></b> (accept <b><u>Ninoy</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Volcano that's 1991 eruption coincided with Typhoon Yunya, leading to hundreds of millions of dollars in damage", "answer": "Mount <b><u>Pinatubo</u> </b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "Second female president who served from 2001 to 2010", "answer": "Gloria Macapagal <b><u>Arroyo</u></b> (accept <b><u>GMA</u></b>)   Peaceful protest that led to the resignation of Joseph Estrada in 2001 (7)  ANSWER: <b><u>Second EDSA</u></b> Revolution (accept <b><u>People Power Revolution II</u></b>; accept <b><u>EDSA II</u></b>; accept <b><u>EDSA 2001</u></b>; do not accept or prompt on \"People Power Revolution\")", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Armed militant group that broke away from the Moro Islamic Liberation Front under the leadership of Ameril Umbra Kato", "answer": "<b><u>Bangsamoro Islamic Freedom Fighters</u></b> (accept <b><u>BIFF</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man forced James Webb of NASA to investigate the existence of the</u></b> <b><u>\"Phillips Report\" after the Apollo 1 disaster. In a debate, this man was told by his</u></b> <b><u>opponent, \"I will not make age an issue of this campaign.\" Karl Rolvaag appointed this</u></b> <b><u>man to fill (+)</u> Hubert Humphrey's Senate seat while Humphrey was vice president. This man questioned, \"Where's the beef?\" to Gary Hart, and he chose (*) </b>Geraldine Ferraro as a running mate. Winning only D.C. and his home state of Minnesota, for ten points, who is this presidential candidate who lost to Ronald Reagan in 1984?", "answer": "Walter \"Fritz\" <b><u>Mondale</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This leader's government outlined seven \"dangerous Western values\" in</u></b> <b><u>\"Document Number 9.\" This leader's namesake form of Socialist thought is presented</u></b> <b><u>as a continuation of the \"Three Represents\" and Scientific Development Perspective.</u></b> <b><u>This leader abolished (+)</u> term limits, effectively allowing him to rule indefinitely. This leader sought to extend his country's influence in Africa and South-Central Asia through infrastructure investment as part of the (*) </b>Belt and Road Initiative. For ten points, name this General Secretary of the Chinese Communist Party.", "answer": "<b><u>Xi</u></b> [[SHEE]] Jinping (prompt on \"Jinping\")", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "<b><u>This decade included the Loans for Shares scheme and the Xerox Affair, in</u></b> <b><u>which $500,000 was found in a Xerox box. During this decade, the Taman Division's</u></b> <b><u>tanks shelled the White House during (+)</u> Black October. Yegor Gaider led \"shock therapy\" liberalizations in this decade, in which Dzhokhar Dudayev [[JOO-car DOO-dai-yehv]] declared (*) </b>Chechnya's [[CHETCH-nee-ahs]] Independence before Vladimir Putin crushed the insurrection. Boris Yeltsin was president of Russia in, for ten points, what decade which included the fall of the USSR?", "answer": "<b><u>1990</u></b>s", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>In his early education at Amasya under the tutoring of Akshamsaddin, this</u></b> <b><u>man was influenced to fulfill his Islamic duty. Portugal sent an expedition to fight this</u></b> <b><u>man at the request of Sixtus IV, in which 800 men led by Antonio Primaldi were taken</u></b> <b><u>to the Hill of Minerva to be executed as martyrs at (+)</u> Otranto. Besides Italy, this man defeated Skanderbeg in Albania and defeated John Hunyadi after the Peace of Szeged was broken. In (*) </b>1453, this man ended the Byzantine Empire by conquering Constantinople. For ten points, name this Ottoman Sultan.", "answer": "<b><u>Mehmed II</u></b> (or <b><u>Mehmed the Conqueror</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This author depicted a legendary noblewoman who sold her soul to feed her</u></b> <b><u>tenants in the verse drama</u> </b><em><b><u>The Countess Cathleen</u></b></em><b><u>. This author was inspired by a</u></b> <b><u>childhood trip to Lough [[LOCK]] Gill to write a poem about wanting to return to a</u></b> <b><u>\"small cabin\u2026 of clay and wattles made.\" Along with Edward (+)</u> Martyn and Lady Gregory, this author founded the Abbey Theatre. This poet reflected on a failed uprising against British rule in the poem (*) </b>\"Easter, 1916.\" For ten points, name this Irish poet, the author of \u201cSailing to Byzantium\u201d and \u201cThe Second Coming.\"", "answer": "William Butler <b><u>Yeats</u></b>", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Poetry"}, {"question": "<b><u>This god was traditionally given fifty names that corresponded to an ancient</u></b> <b><u>list of kings. Bronze Age depictions of this god show him riding on the</u> </b><em><b><u>mushussu</u> </b></em><b><u>dragon. A notable statue of this god was worshipped in the Esagila temple, from</u></b> <b><u>which it was stolen by the (+)</u> Elamites and Assyrians. This son of Ea is depicted slaying a primordial water deity and retrieving the Tablets of Destiny in the (*) </b><em>Enuma Elish</em>. For ten points, name this chief god of the Babylonian pantheon, the slayer of Tiamat.", "answer": "Bel <b><u>Marduk</u></b>", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {"question": "<b><u>The Grand Duchess of Baden enlisted this person\u2019s help in setting up medical</u></b> <b><u>facilities during the four-month siege of Paris by Prussia, and this person was</u></b> <b><u>awarded a Prussian Iron Cross after the Franco-Prussian War. This person innovated</u></b> <b><u>the use of corn (+)</u> husks to act as makeshift bandages during the Battle of Antietam. This person became known as the \u201cFlorence (*) </b>Nightingale of America\u201d during the U.S. Civil War. For ten points, name this founder of the American Red Cross, a nurse known as the \u201cAngel of the Battlefield.\u201d", "answer": "Clara <b><u>Barton</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>The first pope of this name sent a list of sacred books to Exsuperius of</u></b> <b><u>Toulouse that was confirmed by the Canon of Trent nearly a thousand years later. A</u></b> <b><u>\u201cSavior of Hungary\u201d with this name led the Holy League to save Vienna and was burnt</u></b> <b><u>in effigy by the Green Ribbon Club of (+)</u> London Protestants in the Exclusion Crisis. The third pope of this name launched a crusade against Cathars in southern France as well as one that resulted in the 1204 (*) </b>Sack of Constantinople. For ten points, give this name of the Pope who called the Albigensian and Fourth Crusades.", "answer": "<b><u>Innocent</u></b> (accept <b><u>Innocent</u></b> I; accept <b><u>Innocent</u></b> III; accept <b><u>Innocent</u></b> XI)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Reginald Johnston was a tutor in this place and wrote about its</u> </b><em><b><u>Twilight</u></b></em><b><u>.</u></b> <b><u>Vietnamese architect Nguyen An [[WIN AHN]] helped built this location from precious</u></b> <em><b><u>Phoebe zhennan</u></b></em><b><u> [[FEE-bee ZHEN-AHN]] wood. Swastika and (+)</u> Longevity patterns adorn this site which legendarily contains 9999 rooms. Including the Hall of Mental Cultivation, this location's (*) </b>Tiananmen Gate, which connects to the eponymous square, contains a large portrait of Mao Zedong. For ten points, name this ancient imperial palace complex, a \"city\" in Beijing.", "answer": "<b><u>Forbidden</u></b> City (or <b><u>Z\u01d0j\u00ecnch\u00e9ng</u></b>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Architecture"}, {}], "bonuses": []}